Good morning everyone. Welcome to
introduction to deep learning. My name
is Masabali and I will be your shadow
instructor for this course. I'll step in
to give lectures whenever professor make
sure professor retita are unavailable.
Today we'll go over the logistics of the
course and we will set expectations for
this semester.
So in this session we will cover who we
are, what um this course entails,
um the chicken challenge and why is it
hard, the course components and how the
grading works and common sense rules
about collaboration and integrity. By
then you should know where to go for
help, how you'll be evaluated and what
resources are available.
So before we jump into logistics, let's
briefly u motivate why this course
matters. Neural networks and deep
learning are technically the engines
behind many modern AI systems.
So from computer vision and language
models to speech recognition and
reinforcement learning, they dominate
the state-of-the-art performance across
a wide range of tasks.
So you'll see examples
of visual recognition, natural language
tasks, generative models, and more as
the semester progresses.
The same methods are also critical in
self-driving cars.
So now the people running this course
are instructors professor bigsharaj and
professor deta singing
uh and a diverse team of TAs spanning
from Pittsburgh Kegali and Silicon
Valley campuses.
Office hours and updates will be always
posted on the course homepage. So this
course web page you you must keep an eye
on it. You need to check that regularly.
We strongly recommend you meet your TAs
um early whenever you need uh help.
Who's the this course is designed for?
So in order to succeed in this course
actually you need to be really
comfortable with Python programming and
basic machine learning concepts
uh linear algebra and calculus
foundations.
So these are the main general course
topics that we will cover from the
network structures multi-layer
perceptrums
uh CNN's RNN's
um beyond the basics generative models
transformers GANs VAEEs for the
practical focus areas we will focus on
um applications related to computer
vision machine translation
speech recognition.
This course is designed for students who
are ready to commit for to to deep
learning, those who want hands-on
experience, those prepared to implement,
experiment and debug. Um students who
are aiming for uh for research or AI
engineering roles. So if you're just
here to um watch slides, it's you would
really struggle because this class is
implementationheavy.
So you have to keep that in mind.
This course is not easy. A lot of work.
A lot of work. A lot a lot of work. And
not for chickens.
So we repeat that on on purpose.
uh but this course is a lot of fun.
So deep learning blends the theory,
intuition and experimentation. So often
understanding comes from after trying
and trying and trying and failing and
failing. So you need to be ready to code
uh neural networks from scratch uh run
experiments, ask questions. Um
um so every single uh uh component is
here to help you from the quizzes to
help you uh test your uh abilities of
understanding the topics that we're
covering in the lectures and technically
realizing that okay there's something
that I have an issue in so I need to ask
questions. The homeworks are will will
teach you to implement complex networks,
optimize them and put your hands on real
world problems. Uh for none for 85
students projects to expose you to real
world deep learning problems. So anyone
who gets an A in this course is
technically ready for a deep learning
job. So don't worry it's fun if you
stayed engaged.
Components of the course.
So first the lectures. The lectures are
the core concepts and the models. We we
will um there will be live streaming for
remote sections. Lectures will also be
recorded and uploaded to the course
website.
Importance of viewing the lectures. So
even if you think oh I know this topic
you must really watch the lecture
um quizzes actually uh in the lectures
marks depend on viewing the lectures.
So we monitor uh attendance we have
polls in the lectures and some of our
lectures may be conducted entirely over
zoom.
We have weekly quizzes. So questions are
related to to topics that were covered
um in lecture slides. Um
and u these quizzes are released on
Friday, closed on Sundays. Um this may
occasionally shift. We'll keep you
posted, but don't panic. Uh we have 14
total quizzes and we accept the best 12,
so you may skip two.
um because sometimes this is definitely
expected to account for any
circumstances and or inability for you
to work on the quiz. Each quiz has 10
multiple choice questions and we accept
the best three attempts per quiz.
So uh
you have the chance you have lots of
chances. Uh we have recitations,
hackathons and boot camps. So the
recitations are hands-on coding
sessions. We really we strongly
recommend you attend everything the
recitations hackathons and boot camps.
The recitations are for example in the
lecture you learn the theoretical part.
You come to the lab you implement the uh
the concepts from scratch. So you really
learn how to implement this thing and
code it. They're held on uh Fridays in
the lecture room
uh and it really covers implementation
specifics while you follow along. And
the hackathons are held on Saturdays.
Uh they're in person in Pittsburgh and
Kaggali.
And um
uh we will also uh it's a like a giant
office hour with pizza.
So yeah, that's that's encouraging. And
uh the boot camps, we have four boot
camps. So we have one for each homework
plus one for the guided project. So
they're held on Saturdays before the
hackathon. So technically it will just
cover the homework implementations
specifics while you uh follow along. So
for the assignments there will be four
main assignments and bonus homeworks and
autograd bonus. So the main homeworks
all have two parts.
Part one and part two. The part one
actually is autograded problems with the
deterministic solutions. So you just
upload them to auto lab and you get your
score. The part two is just open problem
posted on Kaggle.
Um the homework bonus and the autograd
bonus uh uh there will be some uh bonus
homeworks and they are associated with
some of the homeworks. So there will be
also separate autograd bonus homeworks.
These marks actually will not contribute
to the final grading curves and will
give you the chance to make up for marks
missed elsewhere. So,
um that would be that would be really
great to help you whenever you're
behind.
Study groups, everyone must join a study
group. So each study group will be
assigned a TA mentor for help throughout
the course and we recommend
uh study groups of three to four people.
If you do not have a study group, we
will form one uh for you. So please
please please register via forms. We
will post soon on Piaza.
So for the course project, this is
something very important. So if you're
taking 11785, you will do an original
project, something like your idea or the
mentor's idea. Um this is a great
opportunity to um do things that you
really love
and um
or things that you you're working on. Um
if you're taking 11685 you will do a
project a guided project.
Uh we will uh we uh we will propose that
project
and uh if you're taking 11485 this slide
does not apply to you. So all of these
projects are technically intended to
exercise your ability to comprehend and
implement ideas beyond those covered by
the homeworks or any like let's say hot
topics uh uh you are interested in
working on and learning more about and
you'll have a mentor that will guide you
through that project. So this project
can range range from implementation
evaluation of these cutting edge ideas
from recent papers
problem solving that might lead to
publication if completed. Well, actually
many of our um uh IDL students who uh
worked on uh on their original projects,
they managed to complete that project
and publish
um and you you also have the cha you
will have the chance to work on new
models, learning algorithms, techniques
with proper evaluation
and verification of results from hot
published work.
So
it's um is something that's that's super
cool.
Going extra mile. So attendance actually
counts towards your grade. So this is
not optional.
Polls will track in-class participation
and remote students can use streaming or
recordings, but you must view the
lectures fully for credit. So, we
monitor this because we realized that
the attendance correlates highly and
strongly with success with your success.
So the recitations the recitations zero
um that we posted on YouTube are very
very very very important and they cover
lots of great concepts. So please look
into them as they will give you a big
boost. uh most of them they're related
let's say to losses which is related to
homework 2 P2 um some of them are
related to AWS
uh GCP how to use them how to use Kaggle
so they'll give you uh you'll be really
comfortable to watch them before um we
before the semester starts uh so make
sure uh you keep an eye and uh watch all
of them because they'll really help you
a lot. And we we provided also notebook
exercises.
So this will also help you
um code the thing from scratch.
Um so
and uh yeah, homework one part one has
components intended to help you later in
the course.
How we communicate in this course? We
use piaza and course email for
announcement, clarifications, posting
bugs and questions.
These are some reading materials.
You can look into
study groups. You must join a study
group. Uh each group gets a TA mentor
which will help you uh track progress,
points to resources, guides you whenever
you're stuck. So study groups meet
regularly. Peer learning is actually
essential to in this course. You would
learn from your peers the most.
So make sure uh you engage, you meet
regularly and learn from each others
study group mentors. So every study
group will be assigned a TA mentor
and uh we will make we uh the TA mentor
will make sure to uh track your progress
and if you're in trouble the first thing
you do you just reach out to your TA
mentor. If you feel you're falling
behind, if you feel you're struggling,
if you feel uh pressured, unable to
co-op,
reach out to your mentor. Reach out to
your mentor. We will try our best to
help you. We aim to make this uh a
successful course for all of you. So in
our intro to deep learning IDL
world, everyone performs well enough to
get an A without lowered standards. So
we would like to bring you all up to
where we believe you deserve an A.
Everything about this course is geared
to this objective.
So this is very important. Project group
mentors. So every project group will be
assigned at least one TA mentor which
will track your progress and be in touch
about your project status throughout the
semester and you are allowed to seek an
external mentor who has more expertise
in your topic of interest if you need
more guidance and expertise.
So make sure you um you also consider uh
creating uh project groups uh very
early. Uh you need some uh you need
u some students who have uh kind of
similar interests in in the topic. You
need a mentor that will support you
through that journey who has also uh
similar interest. This will help you
more and more and more. It's it's
actually very important because like uh
the project really helps you to
understand how much you learned
uh from uh from from from the whole
topic and will assess and evaluate your
capabilities of uh being capable of
learning and um
uh doing everything required from you in
this uh in anything related to deep
learning.
So the evaluations so your scores comes
from lecture attendance, weekly quizzes,
uh homework assignments and team
projects for uh subtracts. So this is
not for the 11 485.
So this comp this combination actually
balances between the understanding
application and the creativity.
So for the lecture attendance rule, you
must either attend the lectures in
person or wa watch via zoom. So we get
attendance stats from your
participations during in-class polls uh
use of electronic device using uh during
in-person lectures which is not
permitted except during the polls.
Students in Silicon Valley and in other
time zones where your local time is
before 8:00 a.m. or 5:00 p.m. for the
class
may alternately watch recorded lectures
on MediaTek instead.
But MediaTek records who watched and for
how long. So the entire lectures must be
viewed. So if you viewed on media tech
the lectures of each week must be viewed
before 8:00 a.m. of the Monday following
the following week. So otherwise it does
not count. So the precise mechanism for
computing the class participation score
from attendance will be decided at the
end of the semester. So easy easy peasy.
I would advise to you just at that
weekly quizzes. So slides often contain
a lot more information than what's
presented in class. So quizzes will
contain questions from the from the
topics that are on the slides, not just
presented in the class. Uh we we will
also include topics covered in class but
not on online slides. Sometimes there
will be questions based on latest
research papers in the quiz and we will
provide links to the papers. Um
so don't panic.
Homework part one. The part ones
actually um evaluate your ability to
code neural networks on your own from
scratch. So if you implement all
mandatory and bonus questions of part
one of all homeworks, you will hopefully
have all components necessary to
construct the little neural network
toolkit on your own. So the pietorch
will be your
uh own toolkit which we named it my
torch. So uh this is a great chance
actually uh to be uh able uh of creating
your own own toolkit.
Um the homeworks are autograded so you
must be careful and you follow the
instructions carefully. The autograder
is set up on computer with specific
versions of various packages. So your
code must must confirm to their
restrictions. If not, the autograder
will often fail and give you errors or
zero marks even if your code is
functional on your own computer. So you
need to make sure
um uh to the specific versions and
various packages uh which we will
mention in each of the part ones. Note
you get some bonus points if you submit
also the homework early.
for the portus actually after being like
let's say for each portion you will
create your um the your uh the neural
net the part two is testing actually
your ability to solve complex problems
on real world data sets. So um the the
part one actually tests your ability of
implementing the theoretical parts that
you've learned through lectures and the
part two is testing your ability to
solve the complex problems
which is on on the real world data set
related to the same concepts and topics
of the part one. So they are uh related
to each others. But um the unlike part
ones, the initial early submissions are
required and worth 10 out of 100 points
because we need to make sure that you
have gotten started otherwise you may
delay it a lot. And the remaining and
the remaining 90 out of 100 points are
determined by your final score relative
to the cutoffs.
So our standard cutoffs. So after
uh so the high cutff is 90 points, the
medium cut offs is 70, low cut off 50,
very low 30, no submission zero.
Your score would be linearly
interpolated between cutoffs. So if an
85 accuracy model is for the high cutoff
and 75 is for the medium, a model with
80 accuracy will get 82.5
out of 90 points. So there's a fifth
bonus cut off for extra credits
determined by the highest scoring
student. So if the highest uh accuracy
is 92, the scoring student the the
scoring student will get like 110 out of
100. And anyone between 85 to 92 will
get 100 out of 100 assuming they have 10
bonus points from early submissions.
Um
again for course projects you need to
think about forming project teams as
soon as possible because this will help
you. Your teams could be three to four
students maximum
uh for the 685 two to three students
maximum as it's a guided projects with
clear instructions. Uh for the project
requirements
uh you will submit a report uh first you
will have a you will submit a project
proposal by the proposal deadline which
will be listed on the website. Uh submit
an initial report way through the
semester. So it's like a midterm report.
Then you need to submit an updated
report draft 3 days before the
presentation due date. And then you
submit the final reports like during the
final weeks at the end of the semester.
And you will have to create a video like
make a 5 minute video presentation of
the project at the end of the semester.
All of the students must participate in
that video. Um students from that team.
And the video can be presented by um
could be presented by one some or all
team members. But yeah, we highly
suggest that it should be presented by
all team members and the video should
explain the problem, proposed solution
and evaluation.
You need to defend your project by
answering questions about your video on
piaza. The project is often the most
enjoyable portion of the course.
So as we mentioned earlier, we have 14
quizzes. Bottom two dropped. So for the
assignments we will the first one is
about basic MLPS
uh the second one is about CNN's the
third is about RNN's and the fourth is
about sequence to sequence modeling
uh for the team project for this is not
again for 11485
um we have the midterm report which is
like five
uh and the and then the project
presentation period reviewing 10 and
then the final report is 10 and there's
one mark for attendance.
So the homework deadlines are um there
are uh separate deadlines for part ones
and part twos and homework part twos
they have multiple deadlines. So early
submission deadline they're worth 10% of
part two and affirms you have started
the assignment. on time submission
deadlines determines your eligibility
for full cutoff uh marks late or slack
deadline. So everyone gets up to 10
total slack days does not apply to
initial submissions all bonus points nor
homework uh part ones. You can
distribute them as you want across your
homeworks. And once you use up your
slack days, all subsequent late
submissions will acrew a 10% penalty on
top of any other penalties. Note, Kaggle
leaderboard stop showing updates on full
submission deadline. So, we will
continue to accept submissions until you
run out of your slack days.
So please refer to the course for a
complete set uh of policies.
Now to help assist you faster, please
follow our posting guidelines and watch
for the Piaza pink policy post which is
coming out soon. You need to be be
really really um careful on how to post
on Piaza. So um we really need to help
you as much as possible. We need to
answer very quickly. But with regards to
code related questions on piaza, you
need to really make a good title. You
need to describe the problem concise.
You need to include relevant short code
blocks. Just like don't throw like the
whole notebook and just say okay I have
this error and just you know just paste
the whole error. No, no, no. You should
be really, you know, explain your
debugging process, what you tried, um,
the results you got, the errors and how
the expanded stack traces,
um, what roadblock are you stuck at now?
What do you need from us to help you
understand
um, the thing more?
Last but very critical you are here to
learn not just for high score. So um
like just learn IDL yourself
um not to demonstrate how well you can
pretend to learn. So you're at CMU um
which means you are among the brightest
and best students in the world. You
probably were among the top students in
your peer group and all your life before
you came here. So it will be really an
insult to yourself to lower your
integrity. So try your best honestly. If
you are unsure about something, reach
out to us. It's our job to help you and
make sure um you you understand
everything.
So quizzes must be solved individually.
Homeworks can be discussed. We formed uh
study groups to foster that environment.
But your submitted code must be yours.
Uh plagiarism violates the academic uh
integrity. Um again, if you're unsure
about what's allowed, ask on piaza or in
office hours.
We're excited to take this journey with
you. Deep learning is everywhere, but it
will demands discipline and curiosity.
Stay engaged, ask questions, and let's
make this semester a great ones. Thank
you.